<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Proportional Odds Logisitic Regression on StatLab Articles</title>
    <link>/tags/proportional-odds-logisitic-regression/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Proportional Odds Logisitic Regression on StatLab Articles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/proportional-odds-logisitic-regression/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing the Effects of Proportional-Odds Logistic Regression</title>
      <link>/2017/05/10/visualizing-the-effects-of-proportional-odds-logistic-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/10/visualizing-the-effects-of-proportional-odds-logistic-regression/</guid>
      <description>Proportional-odds logistic regression is often used to model an ordered categorical response. By “ordered”, we mean categories that have a natural ordering, such as “Disagree”, “Neutral”, “Agree”, or “Everyday”, “Some days”, “Rarely”, “Never”. For a primer on proportional-odds logistic regression, see our post, Fitting and Interpreting a Proportional Odds Model. In this post we demonstrate how to visualize a proportional-odds model in R.
To begin, we load the effects package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitting and Interpreting a Proportional Odds Model</title>
      <link>/2015/10/05/fitting-and-interpreting-a-proportional-odds-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/10/05/fitting-and-interpreting-a-proportional-odds-model/</guid>
      <description>Take a look at the following table. It is a cross tabulation of data taken from the 1991 General Social Survey that relates political party affiliation to political ideology. (Agresti, An Introduction to Categorical Data Analysis, 1996)
td { padding:0 15px 0 15px; text-align: center; } caption { font-size: 70% }   Political Ideology by Party Affiliation, from the 1991 General Social Survey       Very Liberal</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>