<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linear Regression on StatLab Articles</title>
    <link>/tags/linear-regression/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linear Regression on StatLab Articles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/linear-regression/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Log Transformations in a Linear Model</title>
      <link>/2018/08/17/interpreting-log-transformations-in-a-linear-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/08/17/interpreting-log-transformations-in-a-linear-model/</guid>
      <description>Log transformations are often recommended for skewed data, such as monetary measures or certain biological and demographic measures. Log transforming data usually has the effect of spreading out clumps of data and bringing together spread-out data. For example, below is a histogram of the areas of all 50 US states. It is skewed to the right due to Alaska, California, Texas and a few others.
hist(state.area)After a log transformation, notice the histogram is more or less symmetric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding 2-way Interactions</title>
      <link>/2016/03/25/understanding-2-way-interactions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/25/understanding-2-way-interactions/</guid>
      <description>When doing linear modeling or ANOVA it’s useful to examine whether or not the effect of one variable depends on the level of one or more variables. If it does then we have what is called an “interaction”. This means variables combine or interact to affect the response. The simplest type of interaction is the interaction between two two-level categorical variables. Let’s say we have gender (male and female), treatment (yes or no), and a continuous response measure.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>