<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on StatLab Articles</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on StatLab Articles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing Type S and Type M Errors</title>
      <link>/2018/10/31/assessing-type-s-and-type-m-errors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/31/assessing-type-s-and-type-m-errors/</guid>
      <description>The paper Beyond Power Calculations: Assessing Type S (Sign) and Type M (Magnitude) Errors by Andrew Gelman and John Carlin introduces the idea of performing design calculations to help prevent researchers from being misled by statistically significant results in studies with small samples and/or noisy measurements. The main idea is that researchers often overestimate effect sizes in power calculations and collect noisy (ie, highly variable) data, which can make statistically significant results suspect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Log Transformations in a Linear Model</title>
      <link>/2018/08/17/interpreting-log-transformations-in-a-linear-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/08/17/interpreting-log-transformations-in-a-linear-model/</guid>
      <description>Log transformations are often recommended for skewed data, such as monetary measures or certain biological and demographic measures. Log transforming data usually has the effect of spreading out clumps of data and bringing together spread-out data. For example, below is a histogram of the areas of all 50 US states. It is skewed to the right due to Alaska, California, Texas and a few others.
hist(state.area)After a log transformation, notice the histogram is more or less symmetric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Matching Methods</title>
      <link>/2018/04/24/getting-started-with-matching-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/24/getting-started-with-matching-methods/</guid>
      <description>A frequent research question is whether or not some “treatment” causes an effect. For example, does taking aspirin daily reduce the chance of a heart attack? Does more sleep lead to better academic performance for teenagers? Does smoking increase the risk of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)?
To truly answer such questions, we need a time machine and a lack of ethics. We would need to be able to take a subject and, say, make him or her smoke for several years and observe whether or not they get COPD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Moderated Mediation</title>
      <link>/2018/03/02/getting-started-with-moderated-mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/02/getting-started-with-moderated-mediation/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post we demonstrated how to perform a basic mediation analysis. In this post we look at performing a moderated mediation analysis.
The basic idea is that a mediator may depend on another variable called a “moderator”. For example, in our mediation analysis post we hypothesized that self-esteem was a mediator of student grades on the effect of student happiness. We illustrate this below with a path diagram.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with Multivariate Multiple Regression</title>
      <link>/2017/10/27/getting-started-with-multivariate-multiple-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/27/getting-started-with-multivariate-multiple-regression/</guid>
      <description>Multivariate Multiple Regression is the method of modeling multiple responses, or dependent variables, with a single set of predictor variables. For example, we might want to model both math and reading SAT scores as a function of gender, race, parent income, and so forth. This allows us to evaluate the relationship of, say, gender with each score. You may be thinking, “why not just run separate regressions for each dependent variable?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>