<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>diagnostic plots on StatLab Articles</title>
    <link>/tags/diagnostic-plots/</link>
    <description>Recent content in diagnostic plots on StatLab Articles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/diagnostic-plots/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Log Transformations in a Linear Model</title>
      <link>/2018/08/17/interpreting-log-transformations-in-a-linear-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/08/17/interpreting-log-transformations-in-a-linear-model/</guid>
      <description>Log transformations are often recommended for skewed data, such as monetary measures or certain biological and demographic measures. Log transforming data usually has the effect of spreading out clumps of data and bringing together spread-out data. For example, below is a histogram of the areas of all 50 US states. It is skewed to the right due to Alaska, California, Texas and a few others.
hist(state.area)After a log transformation, notice the histogram is more or less symmetric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Diagnostic Plots for Linear Regression Analysis</title>
      <link>/2015/09/21/understanding-diagnostic-plots-for-linear-regression-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/09/21/understanding-diagnostic-plots-for-linear-regression-analysis/</guid>
      <description>You ran a linear regression analysis and the stats software spit out a bunch of numbers. The results were significant (or not). You might think that you’re done with analysis. No, not yet. After running a regression analysis, you should check if the model works well for data.
We can check if a model works well for data in many different ways. We pay great attention to regression results, such as slope coefficients, p-values, or R2 that tell us how well a model represents given data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>