<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Text Analysis on StatLab Articles</title>
    <link>/tags/text-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Text Analysis on StatLab Articles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/text-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Ours to Shape Comments, Part 5</title>
      <link>/2019/01/31/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/31/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-5/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the penultimate post of this series, we’ll use some unsupervised learning approaches to uncover comment clusters and latent themes among the comments to President Ryan’s Ours to Shape website.
library(quanteda) # main text packagelibrary(tidyverse) # for dplyr, stringr, piping, etc.library(RColorBrewer) # better colors in graphslibrary(scales) # better breaks and labels in graphslibrary(stm) # structural topic modelsLet’s start with the document-feature matrix we created from the de-duplicated comments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Ours to Shape Comments, Part 4</title>
      <link>/2018/12/19/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/19/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-4/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the fourth installment of this series (we’re almost done, I promise), we’ll look at the sentiment – aka positive/negative tone, polarity, affect – of the comments to President Ryan’s Ours to Shape website.
We don’t have a pre-labeled set of comments, with negative or positive sentiment already identified, so we can’t use a supervised classification method (and I’m not committed enough to hand code a sample of comments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Ours to Shape Comments, Part 3</title>
      <link>/2018/12/18/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/18/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-3/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionTo recap, we’re exploring the comments submitted to President Ryan’s Ours to Shape website (as of December 7, 2018).
In the first post we looked at the distribution of comments across Ryan’s three categories – community, discovery, and service – and across the contributors’ primary connection to the university. We extracted features like length and readability of the comments, and compared these across groups. And we explored the context in which key words of interest (to me) were used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Ours to Shape Comments, Part 2</title>
      <link>/2018/12/14/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/14/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-2/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the last post, we began exploring the Ours to Shape comments – the distribution across categories and contributors, the length and readability of the comments, and a few key words in context. While I did more exploration of the data than reported, the first post gives a taste of the kind of dive into the data that usefully proceeds analysis.
In this post, we’ll start digging into word frequencies, relative frequencies by groups, and distinguishing words.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Ours to Shape Comments, Part 1</title>
      <link>/2018/12/13/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/13/analysis-of-ours-to-shape-comments-part-1/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionAs part of a series of workshops on quantitative analysis of text this fall, I started examining the comments submitted to President Ryan’s Ours to Shape website. The site invites people to share their ideas and insights for UVA going forward, particularly in the domains of service, discovery, and community. The website was only one venue for providing suggestions and voicing possibilities – President Ryan has hosted community discussions as well – but the website afforded an opportunity for individuals to chime in multiple times and at their convenience, so in theory should represent an especially inclusive collection.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>